<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvorming of a mad dogge: or, A soppe for Cerberus the iaylor of Hell No confutation but a sharpe redargution of the bayter of women. By Constantia Munda</title>
            <author>Munda, Constantia.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848272</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvorming of a mad dogge: or, A soppe for Cerberus the iaylor of Hell No confutation but a sharpe redargution of the bayter of women. By Constantia Munda</title>
                  <author>Munda, Constantia.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for Laurence Hayes, and are to be sold at his shop neere Fleet-bridge, ouer against St. Brides Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Constantia Munda is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Swetnam, Joseph.  The araignment of lewde, idle, froward, and unconstant women.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The worming of a madde dogge.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swetnam, Joseph, fl. 1617. --  Arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and unconstant women --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13356:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13356:1"/>
            <p>THE WORMING of a mad Dogge:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A SOPPE FOR <hi>CERBERVS</hi> THE Iaylor of Hell.</p>
            <p>NO CONFVTATION BVT A ſharpe Redargution of the <hi>bayter of Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> CONSTANTIA MVNDA — <hi>dux faemina facti.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg: Aen: 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Sigenus humanum &amp; mortalia temnitis arma,</l>
               <l>At ſperate Deos memores fandi atque nefandi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for LAVRENCE HAYES, and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere Fleet-bridge, ouer againſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Brides</hi> Lane. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13356:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13356:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL LADY her moſt deare Mother, the Lady PRVDENTIA MVNDA, the true <hi>patterne of Pietie and Vertue, C. M.</hi> wiſheth increaſe of happineſſe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS firſt your paines in bearing me was ſuch</l>
               <l>A benefit beyond requitall, that twere much</l>
               <l>To thinke what pangs of ſorrow you ſuſtain'd</l>
               <l>In child-birth, when mine infancy obtain'd</l>
               <l>The vitall drawing in of ayre, ſo your loue</l>
               <l>Mingled with care hath ſhewen it ſelfe, aboue</l>
               <l>The ordinary courſe of Nature: ſeeing you ſtill</l>
               <l>Are in perpetuall <hi>Labour</hi> with me, euen vntill</l>
               <l>The ſecond birth of education perfect me,</l>
               <l>You <hi>Trauaill</hi> ſtill though <hi>Churched</hi> oft you be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In recompence thereof what can I giue,</l>
               <l>But what I take, euen that I liue,</l>
               <l>Next to the heavens 'tis yours. Thus I pay</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13356:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13356:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13356:4"/>My debt by taking vp at intereſt, and lay</l>
               <l>To pawne that which I borrow of you: ſo</l>
               <l>The more I giue I take, I pay, I owe.</l>
               <l>Yet leſt you thinke I forfait ſhall my bond</l>
               <l>I here preſent you with my writing hand.</l>
               <l>Some trifling minutes I vainely did beſtow</l>
               <l>In penning of theſe lines that all might know</l>
               <l>The ſcandals of our aduerſarie, and</l>
               <l>I had gone forward had not <hi>Heſter hang'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haman</hi> before: yet what here I wrote</l>
               <l>Might ſerue to ſtop the curs wide throat,</l>
               <l>Vntill the haltar came, ſince which I ceaſt</l>
               <l>To proſecute what I intended, leſt</l>
               <l>I ſhould be cenſur'd that I vndertooke</l>
               <l>A worke that's done already: ſo his booke</l>
               <l>Hath ſcapt my fingers, but in like caſe</l>
               <l>As a malefactor changeth place</l>
               <l>From Newgate vnto Tiburne, whoſe good hope</l>
               <l>Is but to change his ſhackels for a rope.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although this be a toy ſcarce worth your view,</l>
               <l>Yet deigne to reade it, and accept in lieu</l>
               <l>Of greater dutie, for your gracious looke</l>
               <l>Is a ſufficient Patrone to my booke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is the worſt diſgrace that can be had.</l>
               <l>A Ladies daughter <hi>worm'd a dog that's mad.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Daughter CONSTANTIA MVNDA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13356:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Joſeph Swetnam.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat? is thy ſhameles muſe ſo fleg'd in ſin</l>
               <l>So cocker'd vp in miſchiefe? or haſt bin</l>
               <l>Train'd vp by Furies in the ſchoole of vice,</l>
               <l>Where the licentious Deuils hoyſt the price</l>
               <l>Of vncought miſchiefe, &amp; make a ſet reward,</l>
               <l>For hell-hound ſlanderers that nought regard</l>
               <l>Their reputation, or the wholeſome Lawes</l>
               <l>Of Vertues Common-wealth, but ſeek applauſe</l>
               <l>By rayling and reuiling to depraue</l>
               <l>The mirrour of Creation, to out-braue</l>
               <l>Euen heauen it ſelfe with folly: could the ſtraine</l>
               <l>Of that your barren-idle-donghill braine,</l>
               <l>As from a Chymick Limbeck ſo diſtill</l>
               <l>Your poyſon'd drops of hemlocke, and ſo fill</l>
               <l>The itching eares of ſilly ſwaines, and rude</l>
               <l>Truth-not-diſcerning ruſticke multitude</l>
               <l>With ſottiſh lies, with bald and ribald lines,</l>
               <l>Patcht out of Engliſh writers that combines</l>
               <l>Their higheſt reach of emulation but to pleaſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13356:5"/>The giddy-headed vulgar: whoſe diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Like to a ſwelling dropſie, thirſts to drinke</l>
               <l>And ſwill the puddles of this naſty ſinke:</l>
               <l>Whence through the channels of your muddy wit,</l>
               <l>Your hotch-potcht work is drawn and the ſlimy pit</l>
               <l>Of your inuectiue pamphlet fild to th'brim</l>
               <l>With all defiled ſtreames, yet many ſwimme</l>
               <l>And bath themſelues (oh madnes) in that floud</l>
               <l>Of miſchiefe, with delight, and deem that good</l>
               <l>Which ſpoyls their reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being not vnderſtood.</l>
               <l>When people view not wel your diuelliſh book,</l>
               <l>Like nibling fiſh they ſwallow bait and hooke</l>
               <l>To their deſtruction, when they not deſcry</l>
               <l>Your baſe and moſt vnreuerent blaſphemy.</l>
               <l>How in the ruffe of fury you diſgrace</l>
               <l>(As much as in you lies) and doe deface</l>
               <l>Natures beſt ornament, and thinkſt th'aſt done</l>
               <l>An act deſeruing commendation;</l>
               <l>Whereas thy merits being brought in ſight,</l>
               <l>Exclaime thus on thee, Gallows claime thy right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Woman the crowne, perfection, &amp; the meanes</l>
               <l>Of all mens being, and their well-being, whence</l>
               <l>Is the propagation of all humane kinde,</l>
               <l>Wherein the bodies frame, th'intellect and mind</l>
               <l>With all their operations doe firſt finde</l>
               <l>Their Eſſence and beginning, where doth lie</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13356:5"/>The mortall meanes of our eternity,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertues, worthineſſe, reſplendent rayes</l>
               <l>Of perfect beauty haue alwaies had the praiſe</l>
               <l>And admiration of ſuch glorious wits,</l>
               <l>Which Fame the worlds great Herauld ſits,</l>
               <l>Crowning with Lawrel wreaths &amp; Mittle bows,</l>
               <l>The tribute and reward of learned browes,</l>
               <l>And that this goodly peece of nature be</l>
               <l>Thus ſhamefully deteſted, and thus wrong'd by thee.</l>
               <l>How could your vild vntutour'd muſe infold</l>
               <l>And wrap it ſelfe in enuious, cruell, bold,</l>
               <l>Nay impudent detraction, and then throw</l>
               <l>And hurle without regard your venom'd darts</l>
               <l>Of ſcandalous reuiling, at the hearts</l>
               <l>Of all our female ſexe promiſcuouſly,</l>
               <l>Of commons, gentry, and nobility?</l>
               <l>Without exceptions hath your ſpungie pate</l>
               <l>(Voyd in it ſelfe of all things but of hate)</l>
               <l>Suckt vp the dregs of folly, and the lees</l>
               <l>Of mercenary Paſquils, which doe ſqueeſe</l>
               <l>The glaunders of abuſes in the face</l>
               <l>Of them that are the cauſe that humane race</l>
               <l>Keepes his continuance: could you be ſo mad</l>
               <l>As to depraue, nay to call that bad</l>
               <l>Which God calls good? can your filthy clawes</l>
               <l>Scratch out the image that th'Almighty drawes</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13356:6"/>In vs his pictures? no! things ſimply good,</l>
               <l>Keep ſtil their eſſence, though they be withſtood</l>
               <l>By all the complices of hell: you cannot daunt</l>
               <l>Not yet diminiſh, (how ere you baſely vaunt,</l>
               <l>With bitter termes) the glory of our Sex,</l>
               <l>Nor, as you michingly ſurmize, you vexe</l>
               <l>Vs with your dogged rayling, why! we know;</l>
               <l>Vertue oppos'd is ſtronger, and the foe</l>
               <l>That's queld and foyld, addeth but more</l>
               <l>Triumph to th' conqueſt then there was before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore be aduiſed, ceaſe to raile</l>
               <l>On them that with aduantage can you quaile.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13356:6"/>
            <head>THE WORMING OF <hi>a madde Dogge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE itching deſire of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the preſſe with many ſottiſh and illiterate Libels, ſtuft with all manner of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldry, and ſordid inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when euery foule-mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed male-content may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge his <hi>Licambaean</hi> poyſon in the face of all the world,<note place="margin">Tincta licam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeo ſanguine t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la dabit, Ouid in Ibin.</note> hath broken out into ſuch a diſmall contagion in theſe our dayes, that euery ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tongue and opprobrious witte, like the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Mountebankes will aduance their pedling wares of detracting virulence in the publique <hi>Piatza</hi> of euery Stationers ſhoppe. And Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that was inuented to be the ſtore-houſe of famous wits, the treaſure of Diuine literature, the pandect and maintainer of all Sciences, become the receptacle of euery diſſolute Pamphlet. The nurſery and hoſpitall of euery ſpurious and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious brat, which proceeds from baſe phrene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13356:7"/>braine-ſicke bablers. When <hi>ſcribimus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docti</hi> muſt be the motto of euery one that fooles himſelfe in Print: tis ridiculous! but when <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus inſani</hi> ſhould bee the ſigniture of euery page, tis lamentable our times ſo ſtupidly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and benumd with folly, that wee ſhall verifie the Prouerbe, <hi>L'vſanza commune non è peccato,</hi> ſinnes cuſtome-houſe hath <hi>non ſine priuilegio,</hi> writ vpon his dores, as though community in offence could make an immunitie: No! vſe of ſinne is the ſoules extortion, a biting faenorie that eates out the principle. Yet wofull experience makes it too true, <hi>conſuetudo peccandi tollit ſenſum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catt,</hi> as may bee ſeene by the workes of diuers men that make their pens their penſils to limme out vice that it may ſeeme delicious and amiable; ſo to detract from vertue and honeſty, as though their eſſence were onely in outward appearance of goodneſſe, as if mortality were onely circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed within the conditions, of our ſex, <hi>caelum ipſum petimus ſtultitia,</hi> fooliſh man will reprehend his Creator in the admirable worke of his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſeruation: Woman the ſecond edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Epitome of the whole world, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Tome of that goodly volume compiled by the great God of heauen and earth is moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blurd, and derogatiuely raſed by ſcribling penns of ſauage &amp; vncought monſters. To what an irregular ſtraine is the daring impudence of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d-fold bayards aſpired vnto? that they will preſume to call in queſtion euen the moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute worke compoſed by the worlds great Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13356:7"/>A ſtrange blaſphemy to finde fault with that which the Priuy Councell of the high and mighty Parliament of the inſcrutable <hi>Tri-vnitie</hi> in Heauen determined to be very good.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> To call that imperfect, froward, crooked and peruerſe to make an arraignment and Beare-baiting of that which the Pantocrator would in his omniſcient wiſedome haue to be the conſummation of his bleſſed weekes worke, the end, crowne, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the neuer-ſufficiently glorified crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What is it but an exorbitant phrenſie, and wofull taxation of the ſupreme deitie. Yet wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the greateſt part of the <hi>leſſer world</hi> is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally become the ſubiect of euery pedanticall gooſe-quill.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Euery fantaſticke Poetaſter which thinkes he hath lickt the vomit of his <hi>Coriphaeus</hi> and can but patch a hobling verſe together, will ſtriue to repreſent vnſeemely figments imputed to our ſex, (as a pleaſing theme to the vulgar) on the publique Theatre: teaching the worſer ſort that are more prone to luxurie, a compendious way to learne to be ſinfull. Theſe foule mouth'd raylers, <hi>qui non evident vt corrigant, ſed quaerunt quid reprehendant,</hi> that reprooue not that they might reforme, but pry into actions that they might carpe and cauill: ſo that in this infamous profeſſion they farre exceed the vildeſt kinde of Phariſaicall oſtentation, and ſo ſurmounting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all compariſon railing <hi>Anaxarchus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aut vt Ana archus pila <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuaris in alta. Ouid in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. Benuenuto, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who for his detracting and biting tongue was peſtled to death in a brazen morter. Who as a learned <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>gli miſeri vanno a tentone altreuolte
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13356:8"/>a carpone per facer mercatantia dell' altrui da lor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentata è ſeminata vergogna, impudicamente cereano l'altrui deſhonor erger la meretricia fronte &amp; mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar la impudiche corna:</hi> theſe wretched miſcreants goe groaping, and ſometimes on all foure, to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique with other folkes credits by their owne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged and diſperſed ignominie. That impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſeeke by others diſhonour to ſet a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe face on the matter, and thus to put out their immodeſt hornes to butt at, and gore the name and reputation of the innocent, being ſo beſotted with a baſe and miſerable condition, and blinde in themſelues, they bluſh not in their tongues to carry the gall of <hi>Rabilius,</hi> and in their chaps the poyſon of <hi>Colimachus</hi> in their mouthes, the flame of mount <hi>Aetna</hi> in their eyes, <hi>Iupiters</hi> lightning which he darted at the <hi>Centaures,</hi> in their thoghts <hi>Bellonaes</hi> arrowes, in their ſerpentine words the bitterneſſe of <hi>Sulmo</hi> againſt <hi>Orbecca,</hi> blending and commixing all their diſcourſe with epaticke aloes and vnſauourie ſimples,<note place="margin">Plus aloes quam mellis habent.</note> deriuing all their ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of their venomed Recipes from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries ſhop of the Deuill. Notwithſtanding, as the ſame learned man metaphorically ſpeakes, <hi>Coteſti vſei ſcangerati, cittá ſenza muro, naui ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za gouerno, vaſi ſenza coperto caualli indomiti ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za freno non conſiderano.</hi> Theſe wide open-dores, theſe vnwalled townes, theſe rudderleſſe ſhippes, theſe vncouerd veſſels, theſe vnbrideled horſes doe not conſider that the tongue being a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle member ſhould neuer goe out of that ſame iuory gate, in which, (not without a great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13356:8"/>diuine wiſedome and nature together hath encloſed, it ſignifying that a man ſhould giue him ſelfe eyther to vertuous ſpeech, or prudent ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and not let tongue and pen runne vp and downe like a weaponed madde-man, to ſtrike and wound any without partiality, uery one without exception, to make ſuch an vniuerſall maſſacre (for ſo I may terme it,<note place="margin">Vn coup de lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue eſt p us dan gere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x qu' vn coup de lance. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſeeing words make worſe wounds then ſwords) yet leſt villanie domineere and triumph in furie, wee will manicle your diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute fiſt, that you deale not your blowes ſo vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly. Though feminine modeſty hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd our rareſt and ripeſt wits to ſilence, wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it our greateſt ornament, but when neceſſity compels vs,<note place="margin">Sop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> tis as great a fault and folly <hi>loquenda tacere, vt contra grauis eſt culpa tacenda loqui,</hi> being too much prouoked by arrainments, baytings, and rancarous impeachments of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of our whole ſex, <hi>ſtulta eſt clementia</hi> — <hi>periturae parcere cartae,</hi> opportunity of ſpeaking ſlipt by ſilence, is as bad as importunity vpheld by babling <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Loqui quae de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt meli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quam tacere.</note> Know therefore that wee will cancell your accuſations, trauers your bils, and come vpon you for a falſe inditement, and thinke not tis our waſpiſhneſſe that ſhall ſting you; no ſir, vntill we ſee your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepert ſauſineſſe reformed, which will not be till you doe <hi>make a long letter to vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Literam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we will continue <hi>Iuno'es,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Non ſic abibunt odia viuaces aget violentus iras animus</l>
               <l>Saeuusque dolor aeterna bella pace ſublat â geret.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Notwithſtanding for all your iniuries as <hi>Gelo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13356:9"/>Siracuſanus</hi> anſwered <hi>Syagrius the Spartane, You ſhall not induce mee though ſtird with anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean my ſelfe vnreuerently in the retribution of your iniuries.</hi> You idoll muſe, and <hi>muſing being idle</hi> (as your learned Epiſtle beginneth) ſhall bee no plea to make your viperous ſcandals ſeeme plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>ipſa excuſatio culpa eſt.</hi> Where by the way I note your vntoward nature contrary to all men, for wheras in all others of your ſex by your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, idleneſſe ingendreth loue, in you hate: you ſay in the dedication of your booke to your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes the common ſort of women, that you had little eaſe to paſſe the time withall, but now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you haue baſely wron'gd our wearied and wurried Patience with your inſolent inuectiue madneſſe, you ſhall make a ſimple conuerſion of your propoſition, and take your <hi>paſtime</hi> in <hi>little eaſe:</hi> why? if you delight to ſow thornes, is it not fit you ſhould goe on them bare-foot and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legged. Your idle muſe ſhall be frankt vp, for while it is at liberty, moſt impiouſly it throwes durt in the face of halfe humane kinde.<note place="margin">Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coriola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> when hee ſaw his mother and his wife wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, naturall loue compeld him to leaue ſacking the City for their ſakes, <hi>ab hoc exemplum cape,</hi> but your barbarous hand will not ceaſe to ruine the fenſes, and beleager the forces of <hi>Gynaecia,</hi> not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the mother that brought forth ſuch an vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward whelp into the world as thy ſelfe, playing at blindman-buffe with all, ſcattering thy diſſolute language at whomſoeuer comes next: you neuer heard of a boy, an vnlucky gallowes that threw
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13356:9"/>ſtones in the market-place he knew not whither: the wiſely-cynicke Philoſopher bade him take heed leſt he hit his father. <hi>Nomine mutato narretur fabula de te.</hi> You might eaſily, if you had had the grace, perceiue what vſe to make of it. But you goe forward, pretending you were in great <hi>chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> againſt ſome women, and in the <hi>ruffe</hi> of your furie. Grant one abſurditie, a thouſand follow: Alas (good Sir) wee may eaſily gather you were mightily tranſported with paſſion. Anger and madneſſe differ but in time. Twere a pleaſant ſight to ſee you in your <hi>great</hi> ſtanding <hi>choller</hi> and <hi>furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ruffe</hi> together. Your choller (no doubt) was too great for a Spaniſh <hi>peccadillo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A little ſinne,</note> and your ſhagge <hi>ruffe</hi> ſeemed ſo greeſly to ſet forth your ill-loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king viſage, that none of your ſhee-aduerſaries durſt attempt to confront your follie. But now let vs talke with you in your cold bloud. Now the lees of your furie are ſettled to the bottome, and your turbulent minde is defaecated and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, lets haue a parle with you. What if you had cauſe to be offended with ſome (as I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe all) muſt you needs ſhoot your paper-pellets out of your potgun-pate at all women? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (ſweet Sir) the counſell of <hi>Neſtor</hi> to <hi>Achilles:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore ſortem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineas, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i qui bene temperat optimus eſto.</note>It had beene the part of humanitie to haue ſmothered your anger, hoping amends and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement, and not preſently to wrecke your ſpleene. <hi>Architas</hi> in <hi>Tullie</hi> would haue taught you another leſſon:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuſcul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Quo te inquit modo accepiſſem niſi
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13356:10"/>iratus eſſem?</hi> But you (like a hare-braind ſcold) ſet your clawes in the face of the whole world. But this argues your leuitie ioyn'd with degenerate cowardize: for had you but conſidered with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation that (as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſpeakes)</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2.</note>— nullum memorabile nomen</l>
               <l>Fa minea in poena eſt, nec habet victoria laudem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Tis a poore atchieuement to ouercome a woman, you would neuer haue beene ſo grieuouſly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the ouer-flowing of the gall, neither would the reliſh of your furr'd palate haue beene ſo bitter, as what delicates ſoeuer you taſted ſhould become vnpleaſing. I read of a mad fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which had loſt his goods by ſea, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhips had come into the port at <hi>Athens,</hi> he would take a catalogue of them, and very buſie would he be in making an inuentorie of the goods they brought in and receiued, thinking all to bee his. So you hauing peraduenture had ſome curſt wife that hath giuen you as good as you brought, whatſoeuer faults you eſpie in others, you take that to heart: you run a madding vp and downe to make a ſcrole of female frailties, and an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of meretriciall behauiours, aſcribing them to thoſe that are ioyned in the ſacred bands of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie. Becauſe you haue beene guld with braſſe money, will you thinke no coyne currant? Becauſe you haue ſuffered ſhipwracke, will you diſſwade any from venturing to trafficke beyond Seas? Beſides, you ſhew your ſelfe vniuſt in not obſeruing a ſymmetrie and proportion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge and the offence: for a pelting iniurie ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13356:10"/>not prouoke an opprobrious calumnie; a priuate abuſe of your owne familiar doxies ſhould not breake out into open ſlanders of the religious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron together with the proſtitute ſtrumpet; of the nobly-deſcended Ladies, as the obſcure baſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine that haue bitten you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the chaſte and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt virgins, as well as the diſſolute and impudent harlot. Becauſe women are women, you will doe that in an houre, which you will repent you of all your life time after. Nay rather, if the ruffe of your furie would haue let you lookt ouer it, you would haue diuerted the floud-gates of your poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſtreames that way where you perceiued the common ſhore to run, and not haue polluted and ſtained the cleere and cryſtalline waters. Becauſe women are not women, rather might be a fit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of an ingenious Satyriſt.<note place="margin">Iuuen. Sat.</note> 
               <hi>Cùm alterius ſexus imitata figuram eſt:</hi> the reaſon is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quàm praeſtare poteſt mulier galeata pudorem,</l>
               <l>Quae fugit à ſexu?</l>
            </q>
            <p>But when women are women, when wee ſaile by the true compaſſe of honeſt and religious conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, why ſhould you be ſo doggedly incenſed to barke in generall? why ſhould you imploy your inuention to lay open new faſhions of lewdneſſe, which the worſt of women ſcarce euer were acquainted with? imitating the vice of that Pagan Poet, whoſe indignation made verſes, whoſe filthy reprehenſion opened the doores of vnbridled luxurie, and gaue a preſident of all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired wickedneſſe, and bruitiſh ſenſualitie, to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages;<note place="margin">Scal. <hi>3.</hi> lib. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. cap. <hi>9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> whom great <hi>Scaliger</hi> indeed cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13356:11"/>not worthy to be read of a pious and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man. That <hi>Satyr</hi> brands all his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women with the ſame marke:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Iam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eadem ſummis pariter minimiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> libido eſt,</l>
               <l>Nec melior pedibus ſilicem quae conterit atrum,</l>
               <l>Quàm quae longorum vehitur ceruice Syrorum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But he liued in a nation earthly, deuilliſh, ſenſuall, giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe, that wrought all filthineſſe with greedineſſe. But you, ſir, were whelpt in a better age, at leaſt in a better climate, where the Goſpell is preached, and <hi>the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land;</hi> where you might ſee (if you could perfectly diſtinguiſh) if you were not in the gall of bitterneſſe. Matchleſſe beauties and glorious vertues ſhining together, you might behold (if outragious rage had not drawne a filme ouer your eye-ſight) the goodly habiliments of the minde combined with the perfection of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comelineſſe and ornaments of the body. Is there not as many monuments erected to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous eternizing of charitable deeds of women re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in their generations, as trophees to the moſt couragious Potentates? In the commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of founders and benefactors, how many women haue emulated your ſex in bountifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions to religious vſes and furtherance of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? I might produce infinite examples, if neede were: but bray a foole in a morter (ſaid the wiſe man) yet he will not leaue his foolerie: Neither if whole volumes were compiled againſt your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt calumnies, would you euer be brought to a palinodie and recantation. Wee haue your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13356:11"/>vnder your owne hand, where you ſay you <hi>might haue emploied your ſelfe to better vſe than in ſuch an idle buſineſſe.</hi> True:</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</q>
            <p>A foole ſpeakes ſometimes to the purpoſe. If you muſt needs be digiting your pen, the time had beene farre better ſpent if you had related to the world ſome ſtories of your trauels, with a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man learneder and wiſer then your ſelfe: ſo you might haue beguiled the time, and expoſed your <hi>ridiculous</hi> wit to laughter:<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Quid enim ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iore ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> accipitur v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> you might haue told how hardly ſuch an vnconſtant <hi>bella curtizana de Venetijs</hi> entertained you, how your teeth watered, and after your affections were poiſoned with their hainous euils; how in the beginning of your thirty yeeres trauell and odde,<note place="margin">In his firſt Epiſtle.</note> your conſtitution inclined and you were addicted to prie into the various actions of looſe, ſtrange, lewd, idle, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inconſtant women; how you happened (in ſome Stewes or Brothel houſes) to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their cheats and euaſions; how you came to be ſo expert in their ſubtile qualities; how politikely you caught the daughter in the ouen, yet neuer was there your ſelfe; how in your voyages your ſtomacke was cloyd with theſe ſurfets, and therefore being a traueller, you had reaſon to cenſure hardly of women. Haue you traueld halfe as long againe as that famous Pilgrim, <hi>which knew the faſhions of many men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaw their Cities?</hi> Haue you out-ſtript him in time, and come ſo ſhort of him in knowledge? Is this all the manners you haue learned abroad, theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13356:12"/>thirty and odde yeeres? Is this the benefit of your obſeruations? Is this all the profit your Country ſhall reape by your forraine endeuours? to bring home a company of idle humours of light huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues which you haue noted, and divulge them in print to your owne diſgrace and perpetuall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie? Haue you traueld three times as long as an Elephant, and is this the firſt fruit, nay all the fruit of your idle addle coxcombe? Certainly you miſ-ſpent your time in your trauels: for it had beene more profitable for you, if you had brought dogges from <hi>Iceland;</hi> better for your Countrey, if you had kept a dogge there ſtill. But tis eaſie to giue a reaſon of your exaſperate viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, from your being a traueller: for it is very likely when you firſt went abroad to ſee faſhions, twas your fortune to light amongſt ill company, who trying what metall you were made of, quickly matriculated you in the ſchoole of vice, where you proued a moſt apt <hi>Nov-proficient,</hi> and being guld of your patrimonie, your purſe was turned into a paſſe, and that by women. Like a dogge that bites the ſtone which had almoſt beat out his braines, you come home ſwaggering:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Prodiga non ſentit pereuntem foemina cenſum,</l>
               <l>At velut exhauſta redivivus pullulet arca</l>
               <l>Nummus, &amp; è pleno ſemper tollatur aceruo,</l>
               <l>Non vnqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reputant quantum ſibi gaudia conſtant.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which if you cannot vnderſtand, is to this ſenſe:</p>
            <q>
               <l>A lauiſh woman thinkes there is no ſtint</l>
               <l>Vnto her purſe: as though thou hadſt a mint,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13356:12"/>She caſts no count what money ſhee'l beſlow,</l>
               <l>As if her coine as faſt as t'ebd, did ſlow.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Such it may be (I ſpeake but on ſuſpicion) were the conditions of thoſe minions your minoritie had experience of in your voyages. Wherefore none either good or bad, faire or foule, of what eſtate ſoeuer, of what parentage or royall deſcent and lineage ſoeuer, how well ſoeuer nurtured and qualified, ſhall ſcape the conuicious violence of your prepoſterous procacitie. Why did you not ſnarle at them directly that wronged you? Why did not you collimate your infectious Iauelins at the right marke? If a theefe take your purſe from you, will you maligne and ſwagger with euery one you meet? If you be beaten in an Ale-houſe, will you ſet the whole Towne afire? If ſome cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans that you haue met with in your trauels (or rather that haue met with you) haue ill intreated you, muſt honeſt and religious people be the ſcope of your malicious ſpeeches and reprochfull tearmes? Yet it may be you haue a further drift, to make the world beleeue you haue an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift of continencie; ſoothing your ſelfe with this ſuppoſition, that this open reuiling is ſome token and euidence you neuer were affected with delicate and effeminate ſenſualitie, thinking this pamphlet ſhould aſſoile thee from all manner of leuie and taxation of a laſciuious life; as if, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you cynically raile at all both good and bad, you had beene hatcht vp without concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence; as if nature had beſtowed on you all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Concupiſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Twas ſpoken of <hi>Euripides,</hi> that he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13356:13"/>hated women in <hi>choro,</hi> but not in <hi>thoro,</hi> in <hi>calamo,</hi> but not in <hi>thalamo:</hi> and why cannot you be liable to the ſame obiection? I would make this excuſe for you, but that the crabbedneſſe of your ſtile, the vnſauory periods of your broken-winded ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences perſwade your body to be of the ſame temper as your minde. Your ill-fauoured coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, your wayward conditions, your peeuiſh and pettiſh nature is ſuch, that none of our ſex with whom you haue obtained ſome partiall conference, could euer brooke your dogged frompard frowardneſſe: vpon which male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented deſperation, you hanged out your flagge of defiance againſt the whole world, as a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous monſtrous rebell againſt nature. Beſides, if your curriſh diſpoſition had dealt with men, you were afraid that <hi>Lex talionis</hi> would meet with you;<note place="margin">Like for like.</note> wherefore you ſurmized, that inueighing againſt poore illiterate women, we might fret and bite the lip at you, wee might repine to ſee our ſelues baited and toſt in a blanket, but neuer durſt in open view of the vulgar either diſcloſe your blaſphemous and derogatiue ſlanders, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the vntainted puritie of our glorious ſex: nay, you'l put gagges in our mouthes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure vs all to ſilence: you will firſt abuſe vs, then binde vs to the peace; wee muſt be tongue-tied, leſt in ſtarting vp to finde fault, wee proue our ſelues guiltie of thoſe horrible accuſations. The ſinceritie of our liues, and quietneſſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is a wall of braſſe to beat backe the bullets of your vituperious ſcandals in your owne face.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13356:13"/>Tis the reſolued Aphoriſme of a religious ſoule to anſwere, <hi>ego ſic viuam vt nemo tibi fidem adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat:</hi> by our well-doings to put to ſilence the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of fooliſh men, as the Poet ſpeakes;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Viuendum recte tum propter plurima, tum de his</l>
               <l>Praecipue cauſis vt linguas mancipiorum contemnas.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Liue well for many cauſes, chiefly this,</l>
               <l>To ſcorne the tongue of ſlaues that ſpeake amiſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Indeed I write not in hope of reclaiming thee from thy profligate abſurdities, for I ſee what <hi>a pitch</hi> of diſgrace and ſhame thy ſelfe-pining en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie hath carried thee to,<note place="margin">Vnde altior eſſet caſus &amp; impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae praeceps im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ruine.</note> for thy greater vexation and more perplexed ruine. You ſee your blacke grinning mouth hath beene muzled by a modeſt and powerfull hand, who hath iudiciouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed, and wiſely layed open your ſingular ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, couched vnder incredible impudence, who hath moſt grauely (to ſpeake in your owne language) <hi>vnfoulded euery pleat, and ſhewed euery rinckle</hi> of a prophane and brutiſh diſpoſition, ſo that tis a doubt whether ſhee hath ſhewed more modeſty or grauity, more learning or prudence in the religious confutation of your vndecent ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. But as ſhee hath beene the firſt Champion of our ſexe that would encounter with the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous bloudhound, and wiſely dammed vp your mouth, and ſealed vp your iawes leſt your veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med teeth like madde dogges ſhould damage the credit of many, nay all innocent damoſels; ſo no doubt, if your ſcurrilous and deprauing tongue breake priſon, and falls to licking vp your vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13356:14"/>poyſon, to the end you may ſquirt out the ſame with more pernicious hurt, aſſure your ſelfe there ſhall not be wanting ſtore of Helebore to ſcoure the ſinke of your tumultuous gorge, at leaſt we will cram you with Antidotes and Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potions, that if you ſwell not till you burſt, yet your digeſted poyſon ſhall not be contagious. I heare you foame at mouth and groule againſt the Author with another head like the triple dog of hell, wherefore I haue prouided this ſop for <hi>Cerberus,</hi> indifferent well ſteept in vineger. I know not how your pallat will bee pleaſed with it to make you ſecure hereafter. Ile take the paines to worme the tongue of your madneſſe, and daſh your rankling teeth downe your throat: tis not houlding vp a wiſpe, nor threatning a cucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole ſhall charme vs out of the compaſſe of your chaine, our pens ſhall throttle you, or like <hi>Archilochus</hi> with our tart Iambikes make you <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pez</hi> his godſon: we will thruſt thee like <hi>Phalaris</hi> into thine owne brazen bull, and baite thee at thy owne ſtake, and beate thee at thine owne weapon, <hi>Quippe minuti ſemper &amp; infirmi eſt animi exigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que voluptas vltio: continuo ſic collige quod vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta nemo magis gaudet quam faemina.</hi> Tis your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets owne aſſertion, that vltion being the delight of a weake and feeble minde belongs to vs.<note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m diri con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>s;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> facti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abet a to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſurdo verbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> caedit. Occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quatieute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nimo tortore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>agellum.</note> Thou that in thy ſelfe feeleſt the laſh of folly, thou that confeſſeſt thy ſelfe to be in a fault, nay that thou haſt offended beyond ſatisfaction, for tis hard to giue a recompence for a ſlander: thou that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeſt thy ſelfe to be madde, in a rough fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13356:14"/>your wits gon a woolgathering that you had forgot your ſelfe (as I think) <hi>Nero</hi>-like in ripping vp the bowels of thine owne Mother: for I haue learnt ſo much Logicke to know <hi>quicquid dicitur de ſpecie, dicitur de vnoquo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> indiuiduo eiuſdem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciei:</hi> whatſoeuer is ſpoken or praedicated of the kinde is ſpoken of euery one in the ſame kinde: firſt therefore to bring you to an impious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or inconuenience. Is it not a comely thing to heare a Sonne ſpeake thus of his mother: <hi>My mother in her furie was worſe than a Lion being bitten with hunger, than a beare being robbed of her yong ones, the viper being trod on. No ſpur would make my mother go, nor no bridle would hold her backe: tell her of her fault, ſhe will not beleeue ſhe is in any fault: giue her good counſell, but ſhe will not take it: if my Father did but look after another woman, then ſhe would be iealous: the more he loued her, the more ſhee would diſdaine him: if he threatned her, ſhee would bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry: when he flattered her, then ſhe would be proud: if he forbore her, it made her bould: if hee chaſtened her, ſhe would turne to a ſerpent: at a word, my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would neuer forget an iniury, nor giue thankes for a good turne: what an aſſe then was my Father to exchange gould for droſſe, pleaſure for paine: tis a wonderfull thing to ſee the madde feates of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for ſhe would picke thy pocket, empty thy purſe, laugh in thy face &amp; cut thy throat, ſhe is vngratefull, periurd, full of fraud, flouting, and deceit, vnconſtant waſhpiſh, toyiſh, light, ſullen, proud, diſcourteous and cruell: the breaſt of my mother was the harbourer of an enuious heart, her heart the ſtorehouſe of poyſoned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13356:15"/>hatred, her head deuiſed villany, and her hands were ready to put in practiſe what her heart deſired, then who can but ſay but my mother a woman ſprung from the Deuill?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>you from your mother, and ſo Swetnam is the Deuils Grand-child.</hi> Doe you not bluſh to ſee what a halter you haue purchaſed for your owne necke? You thought in your ruffe of furie like <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> to make an edict that all the world ſhould be taxed, when your ſelfe is tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to the greateſt infirmities: you blowed the fier of ſedition with the bellowes of your anger, and the coales are burning in your owne boſome, <hi>Periculoſo plenum opus alea, tractas &amp; incedis per ignes ſuppoſitos cineri doloſo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Is there no reuerence to be giuen to your mother becauſe you are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from her teat, and neuer more ſhall be fedde with her pappe? You are like the rogue in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which was going to the gallowes for burgla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that bit off his mothers noſe, becauſe ſhe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed him not in his infancy for his pettie-Larce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: is this the requitall of all her coſt, charge, care, and vnſpeakeable paines ſhe ſuffered in the producing of ſuch a monſter into the light? If ſhe had cram'd grauell downe thy throat when ſhee gaue thee ſucke, or expoſed thee to the mercy of the wilde beaſts in the wilderneſſe when ſhe fed thee with the pap, thou couldſt not haue ſhowen thy ſelfe more vngratefull then thou haſt in bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out thy nefarious contempt of thy mothers ſexe.<note place="margin">Ingratum ſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eero <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnia di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ro.</note>Wherefore mee thinkes it is a pleaſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge that thy ſoule arraines thee at the barre of conſcience, and thy diſtracted mind cannot chuſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13356:15"/>but hant thee like a bumbaylie to ſerue a <hi>ſub paena</hi> on thee, the ſtile and penning of your pamphlet hath brought you within the compaſſe of a <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire,</hi> and euery ſentence beeing ſtolne out of other bookes, accuſeth you of robbery. So that thou carrieſt in thy ſelfe a walking Newgate vp &amp; downe with thee, thy owne perplexed ſuſpicions like <hi>Promotheus</hi> vulture is alwaies gnawing on thy liuer. Beſides, theſe books which are of late come out (the latter whereof hath preuented me in the deſignes I purpoſed in running ouer your wicked handi-worke) are like ſo many red-hot irons to ſtigmatize thy name with the brand of a hideous blaſphemer and incarnate Deuill. Although thou art not apprehended and attached for thy villany I might ſay fellonie, before a corporall iudge, yet thine owne conſcience if it be not ſeared vp, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thee, and wracks thy tempeſtuous minde with a diſſolution and whurring too and fro of thy ſcandalous name, which without blemiſh my penne can ſcarce deigne to write, you finde it true which the Poet ſpeakes;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Exemplo quodeunque malo committitur, ipſi</l>
               <l>Diſplicet authori, prima eſt haec vltio quod ſe</l>
               <l>Iudice nemo nocens abſoluitur, improba quamuis</l>
               <l>Gratia fallacis praetoris vicerit vrnam.<note place="margin">Iuuen: Sat: <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>What ſin is wrought by ill example, ſoone</l>
               <l>The diſpleaſed Author wiſheth it vndone.</l>
               <l>And tis reuenge when if the nocent wight,</l>
               <l>Vmpires his cauſe himſelfe: in his owne ſight,</l>
               <l>He findes no abſolution, though the eyes</l>
               <l>Of iudgement wink, his ſoule ſtill guilty cries.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13356:16"/>Tis often obſerued, that the affections of audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (and readers too) are more offended with the ſoule mouthed reproofe of the brawling accuſer, than with the fault of the delinquent. If you had kept your ſelfe within your pretended limits, and not medled with the blameleſſe and innocent, yet your preiudicate rayling would rather argue an vnreuerent and laſciuious inclination of a depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nature, then any loue or zeale to vertue and honeſty: you ought to haue conſidered that in the vituperation of the miſdemeanors and diſorders in others lines; this cautelous <hi>Prouiſo</hi> ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you that in ſeeking to reforme others, you deforme not your ſelfe; eſpecially by mouing a ſuſpition that your minde is troubled and feſtered with the impoſtume of inbred malice, and corrupt hatred: for tis alwaies the badge and cogniſance of a degenerous and illiberali diſpoſition to bee ambitious of that baſe and ignoble applauſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the giddy-headed Plebeians, that is acquired by the miſerable oppreſſing and pilling of vertue. But euery wrongfull contumely &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach hath ſuch a ſharpe ſting in it, that if it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten once on the minde of a good and ingenuous nature, tis neuer drawen forth without anxiety &amp; perpetuall recordation of dolour, which if you had known, your hornet-braines would not haue buzd abroad with a reſolution to ſting ſome tho you loſt your ſting and died for it: you would not like the cuttle fiſh ſpewd out your inkie gall with hope to turne the pureſt waters to your owne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hew; <hi>vt non odio inimicitiarum ad vituperandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13356:16"/>ſed ſtudio calumniandi ad inimicitias deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deres,</hi> that you would arme your ſelfe, not with the hate of enmity to diſpraiſe vice, but with the ſtudy of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny to make enmity with vertue: yet tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable that ignorance &amp; impudence were part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in your worke, for as you haue of all things vnder the ſunne, ſelected the bayting, or as you make a ſilly ſolaeciſme the bearebayting of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be the tenterhookes whereon to ſtretch your ſhallow inuentions on the triuiall ſubiect of euery ſhackragge that can but ſet penne to paper: ſo in the handling of your baſe diſcourſe, you lay open your imperfections, <hi>arripiendo maledicta ex triuio,</hi> by heaping together the ſcraps, fragments, and reuerſions of diuers engliſh phraſes, by ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping together the glaunders and offals of abuſiue termes, and the refuſe of idle headed Authors, and making a mingle-mangle gallimauphrie of them. Lord! how you haue cudgeld your braines in gleaning multitudes of ſimilies as twere in the field of many writers, and thraſht them together in the floure of your owne deuizor; and all to make a poore confuſed miſceline, whereas thine owne barren ſoyled ſoyle is not able to yeeld the leaſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruity of ſpeech. Tis worthy laughter what paines you haue taken in turning ouer <hi>Pariſmus,</hi> what vſe you make of the <hi>Knight of the Sunne,</hi> what collections out of <hi>Euphues, Amadis a Gaule,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Don Quixotes</hi> Library, ſometimes exact tracing of Aeſopicall Fables, and <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> with the like ſchooleboyes bookes, ſo that if theſe Pamphleters would ſeuerally plucke
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13356:17"/>a crow with you. <hi>Furtiuis nudata coloribus moucat cornicula riſum,</hi> let euery bird take his owne fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you would be as naked as <hi>Aeſops</hi> iay. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you haue ſhewen as much foolery as robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in feathering your neaſt, which is a cage of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane birds, and a ſtorehouſe for the off-ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of other writers. Your indiſcretion is as great in the laying together, &amp; compiling of your ſtolne ware, as your blockiſhneſſe in ſtealing, for your ſentences hang together like ſand without lime: you bring a great heape of ſtony rubbiſh compariſons one vpon the necke of another, but they concurre no more to ſenſe, then a company of ſtones to a building without morter, and tis a familiar Italian Prouerb, <hi>duro è duro non famuro,</hi> hard and hard makes no wall, ſo your hard dull pate hath collected nothing that can ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with common ſenſe, or be pleaſing to any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined diſpoſition, rough and vnhewen morſells digd out of others quarries, potſherds pickt out of ſundry dunghills: your mouth indeed is full of ſtones, <hi>lapides loqueris,</hi> but not ſo wiſely nor ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily cramd in as the geeſe that flie ouer the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in Silicia, which carry ſtones in their beakes leſt their cackling ſhould make them a pray to the Eagles, where you might learne witte of a gooſe.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>Either ſpeake peace, or hold your peace. Is it not irkſome to a wiſe and diſcreet iudgement, to heare a booke ſtuft with ſuch like ſenſe as this, <hi>The world is not made of oatmeale?</hi> I haue heard of ſome that haue thought the world to haue beene
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13356:17"/>compoſed of atomes, neuer any that thought it made of oatmeale: <hi>Nor all is not gold that gliſters, nor the way to heauen is ſtrewd with ruſhes, for a dramme of pleaſure an ounce of paine, for a pint of hony a gallon of gall, for an inch of mirth an ell of moane, &amp;c.</hi> None aboue the ſcumme of the world could endure with patience to reade ſuch a medly compoſed of diſcords. Sometimes your dogrill rhymes make mee ſmile, as when you come,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Man muſt be at all the coſt,</l>
               <l>And yet liue by the loſſe:</l>
               <l>A man muſt take all the paines,</l>
               <l>And women ſpend all the gaines:</l>
               <l>Their catching in ieſt,</l>
               <l>And keeping in earneſt.</l>
               <l>And yet ſhe thinkes ſhe keepes her ſelfe blameleſſe,</l>
               <l>And in all ill vices ſhe would goe nameleſſe.</l>
               <l>But if ſhe carry it neuer ſo cleane,</l>
               <l>Yet in the end ſhe will be counted for a cunny-catching queane.</l>
               <l>And yet ſhe will ſweare that ſhe will thriue,</l>
               <l>As long as ſhe can finde one man aliue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I ſtand not to deſcant on your plaine ſong; but ſurely if you can make ballads no better, you muſt be faine to giue ouer that profeſſion: for your Muſe is wonderfully defectiue in the bandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeres, and you may ſafely ſweare with the Poet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec fonte labra prolui caballino,</l>
               <l>Nec in bicipiti ſomniaſſe Parnaſſo</l>
               <l>Memini. —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Sometimes you make me burſt out with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when I ſee your contradictions of your ſelfe;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13356:18"/>I will not ſpeake of thoſe which others haue eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, although I had a fling at them, leſt I ſhould <hi>actum agere.</hi> Mee thinkes, when you wrote your ſecond Epiſtle, neither to the wiſeſt Clerke, nor yet to the ſtarkeſt foole, the giddineſſe of your head bewrayes you to be both a ſillie Clerke, and a ſtarke foole: or elſe the young men you write to muſt be much troubled with the megrim and the dizzineſſe of the braine: for you beginne as if you were wont to runne vp and downe the Countrey with Beares at your taile. If you meane to ſee the Beare-baiting of women, then trudge to this Beare-garden apace, and get in betimes, and view euery roome where thou maiſt beſt ſit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now you ſuppoſe to your ſelfe the giddy-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded young men are flockt together, and placed to their owne pleaſure, profit, and hearts eaſe. Let but your ſecond cogitations obſerue the method you take in your ſuppoſed ſport: In ſtead of bringing your Beares to the ſtake, you ſay, I thinke it were not amiſſe to driue all women out of my hearing, for doubt leſt this little ſparke kindle into ſuch a flame, and raiſe ſo many ſtinging hornets humming about mine eares, that all the wit I haue (which is but little) will not quench the one, nor quiet the other. Doe yee not ſee your apparant contradiction? <hi>Spectatum admiſsi riſum teneatis amici?</hi> You promiſe your ſpectators the Beare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baiting of women, and yet you thinke it not amiſſe to driue all women out of your hearing; ſo that none but your ſelfe the ill-fauoured Hunckes is left in the Beare-garden to make your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13356:18"/>inuited gueſts merry: whereupon it may very likely be, the eager young men being not willing to be guld and cheated of their money they paid for their roome, ſet their dogges at you, amongſt whom <hi>Cerberus</hi> that hell-hound appeared, and you bit off one of his heads; for preſently after you call him the two-headed dogge, whom all the Poets would faine to haue three heads: You therefore hauing ſnapt off that ſame head, were by the ſecret operation of that infernal ſubſtance, conuerted into the ſame eſſence: and that may ſerue as one reaſon that I tearme you <hi>Cerberus</hi> the Iaylor of hell; for certainly <hi>Quic quid dicitur de toto, dicitur de ſingulis partibus:</hi> That which is ſpoke of the whole, is ſpoken of euery part; and euery limbe of the deuill is an homogeneall part. Doe yee not ſee (goodman woodcocke) what a ſpringe you make for your owne ſelfe? Whereas you ſay tis a great diſcredit for a man to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a ſcold, and that you deale after the manner of a ſhrew, which cannot eaſe her curſt heart but by her vnhappy tongue; obſerue but what concluſion demonſtratiuely followes theſe premiſes:</p>
            <q>
               <l>A man that is accounted a ſcold, hath great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> is accounted a ſcold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo, Ioſeph</hi> hath great diſcredit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If you denie the <hi>Minor,</hi> tis proued out of your owne aſſertion, becauſe you deale after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a ſhrew, &amp;c. where wee may note firſt a corrupt fountaine, whence the polluted puddles
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13356:19"/>of your accuſtomed actions are deriued, <hi>A curſt heart;</hi> then the curſedneſſe of your booke (which if you might be your owne Iudge, deſerues no more the name of a booke, then a Colliers Iade to be a Kings Steed) to bee the fruit of an vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie tongue: thirdly, your commoditie you reape by it, diſcredit. Nay if you were but a maſculine ſcold, twere tolerable; but to be a prophane rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Rahſhekeh,</hi> tis odious. Neither is this all your contrarietie you haue included: for preſently after you profeſſe you wrote this booke with your hand, but not with your heart; whereas but iuſt now you confeſt your ſelfe to deale after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a ſhrew, which cannot otherwiſe eaſe your curſt heart, but by your vnhappy tongue: ſo your hand hath proued your vnhappy tongue a lier. This vnſauorie non-ſenſe argueth you to be at that time poſſeſt with the fault you ſay commonly is in men, to wit, drunkenneſſe, when you wrote theſe iarring and incongruous ſpeeches, whoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities accrew to ſuch a tedious and infinite ſumme, that if any would exactly trace them out, they ſhould finde them like a Mathematicall line, <hi>Diuiſibilis in ſemper diuiſibilia.</hi> Twould put downe the moſt abſolute Arithmetician to make a cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of them: wherefore I could wiſh thee to make a petition, that you might haue your bookes called in and burnt; for were it not better that the fire ſhould befriend thee in purifying the traſh, and eating put the canker of thy defamation, then thy execrable deſignes and inexcuſable impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould blazon abroad thy drunken teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13356:19"/>and temulent foole-hardineſſe to future ages, then thy booke ſhould peremptorily witneſſe thy open and Atheiſticall blaſphemy againſt thy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator euen in the very threſhold and entrance? but aboue all, where thou doeſt put a lie on God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with this ſuppoſition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>If God had not made them only to be a plague to man, he would neuer haue called them neceſſary euils:</hi> Which I thus antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate; But God neuer called them neceſſary euils, Therefore God made them not to be a plague to man. Or elſe turning the concluſion to the meane thus: But God did not make them to be a plague, but a helper and procurer of all felicitie; therefore God neuer called them neceſſary euils. Were it not (I ſay) farre better for you that your laborious idle worke ſhould be aboliſhed in the flames, then it ſhould publikely ſet forth the apert violation of holy writ in ſundry places? one in the beginning (as I remember) where you falſly auerre, that the bleſſed Patriarke <hi>Dauid</hi> exclaimed bitterly againſt women, and like the tempting deuill you alledge halfe Scripture, whereas the whole makes againſt your ſelfe: for thus you affirme he ſaith; <hi>It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be a doore-keeper, than to be in the houſe with a froward woman.</hi> In the whole volume of the booke of God, much leſſe in the Pſalmes, is there any ſuch bitter exclamation? But this is the dittie of the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereby he did inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his loue vnto the houſe of God, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the pauilions of the vnrighteous by this Antitheſis: <hi>It is better to be a doore-keeper in the houſe of the Lord, than to dwell in the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13356:20"/>of the vngodly.</hi> Now if you haue a priuate ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that may interpret by enthuſiaſmes, you may confine the Tabernacles of the vngodly onely to froward women; which how abſurd and groſſe it is, let the reader iudge. Doeſt thou not bluſh (graceleſſe) to peruert (with <hi>Elemas</hi>) the ſtrait wayes of God, by prophaning the Scriptures, and wreathing their proper and genuine interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to by-ſenſes, for the boulſtering and vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of your damnable opinion? beſides thy pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully wronging of the Philoſophers, as <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> &amp;c. whom your illiterate and clowniſh Muſe neuer was ſo happy to know whether they wrote any thing or no. Your eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke hiſtories, although they rather make againſt men than women, yet in your relation you moſt palpably miſtake, and tell one thing for another, as of <hi>Holophernes, Antiochus, Hannibal, Socrates,</hi> and the reſt which the poore deluded <hi>Corydons</hi> and ſillie ſwaines account for oracles, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as axiomes. The quirkes and crotchets of your owne pragmaticall pate, you father on thoſe ancient Philoſophers that moſt extremely oppoſe your conceit of mariage: for <hi>Plato</hi> made this one of his lawes, that whoſoeuer was not maried at thirty fiue yeeres of age, ſhould be puniſhed with a fine. Further he implies a neceſſitie of mariage, euen in regard of the adoration of God himſelfe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Tis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that there ſhould be a lawfull generation and education of children, that life as a lampe may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13356:20"/>continue to poſteritie, that ſo there might alwaies be ſome to worſhip God. What more diuinely or religiouſly could be ſpoken by a Paynim? How then durſt you ſay that the Philoſophers that liued in the old time had ſo hard an opinion of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, that they tooke no delight therein, ſeeing the chiefe of them were maried themſelues? I could be infinite to produce examples and ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles to make you a lier in print: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Theognis.</note> Nothing is more ſweet than a good wife. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Protagoras.</note> He that hath a good wife, hath a merry life. Moſt famous is that retortion of <hi>Pittachus,</hi> one of the ſeuen wiſe men of <hi>Greece,</hi> when he demanded a fellow wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would not take to him a wife, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If I take a faire wife, I ſhall haue her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; if a foule, a torment. The wiſe man replied, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, If thou getſt a foule wife, thou ſhalt not haue her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; if a faire, no torments. There is as much reaſon for the one as the other: but tis but wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting paper to reckon vp theſe obuious ſayings. Let that ſame acclamation of <hi>Horace</hi> ſtand for a thouſand others:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Foelices ter &amp; ampliùs,</l>
               <l>Quos irrupta tenet copula, nec malis</l>
               <l>Divulſus querimonijs,</l>
               <l>Suprema citiùs ſoluet amor die.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Thriſe and more times are they bleſt,</l>
               <l>That in wedlockes bands doe reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13356:21"/>Whoſe faithfull loues are knit ſo ſure,</l>
               <l>That blameleſſe endleſſe they endure.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But you that will traduce the holie Scriptures, what hope is there but you will depraue humane authors. You taxe <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> of a laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious life that by the light of naturall reaſon were chiefeſt eſtabliſhers of Matrimony, both in regard of <hi>oeconomicke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> de leg: Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>politicke</hi> affaires. doe theſe things deſerue commendations of any, but rather the ſcorne and reproofe of all: what a ſilly thing it is, let Monſieur <hi>Swetnam</hi> iudge, when <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> relates in his 4. booke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 49.</note> a hiſtory of one <hi>Tiberius Gracchus,</hi> that found two ſerpents in his bed-chamber and killed the male, which by the prediction of South ſayers deſigned himſelfe to death, becauſe he dearely loued his wife <hi>Cornelia,</hi> and you like an Aſſe tel this tale of <hi>Valerius Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> as if becauſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> tells a tale of one <hi>Bias</hi> that bought the beſt and worſt meate which was tongues, in the market: hee that reades it ſhould ſay that one lying Aſſe <hi>Swetnam</hi> bought the beſt and worſt tongues; but certainely if that <hi>Bias</hi> had met with your tongue in the Market, hee would haue taken it for the worſt and moſt vnprofitable meat, becauſe from nothing can come worſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome then from it: What ſhould I ſpeake of the figments of your dull pate, how abſurdly you tell of one <hi>Theodora</hi> a Strumpet in <hi>Socrates</hi> time, that could intiſe away all the Philoſophers Schollers from him: is not the vaine and inconſtant nature of men more culpable by this enſample than of women, when they ſhould be ſo luxuriouſly bent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13356:21"/>that one ſilly light woman ſhould draw a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of learned Schollers from the right way: yet neyther <hi>Laertius,</hi> nor any that writte the liues of Philoſophers make mention of this <hi>Theodora,</hi> but I haue read of a glorious Martyr of this name, a Virgin of Antiochia, in the time of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the Emperor, who being in priſon, a certaine barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Souldier moued with luſt in himſelfe, and the luſtre of her beauty, would haue rauiſhed her by violence, whom ſhe not onely deterred from this curſed act by her perſwaſiue oratory, but by her powerfull intreaties by changing veſtments wrought her deliuery by him. I would runne through all your ſilly diſcourſe, and anatomize your baſery, but as ſome haue partly beene boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out already, and are promiſed to be proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo I leaue them as not worthy rehearſall or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation. I would giue a <hi>ſuperſede as</hi> to my quill: but there is a moſt pregnant place in your booke which is worthy laughter that comes to my mind where you moſt graphically deſcribe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and antipathie of man and woman, which being conſidered, you thinke it ſtrange there ſhould be any reciprocation of loue, for a man ſay you delights in armes, and hearing the ratling drum, but a woman loues to heare ſweet muſicke on the Lute, Cittern, or Bandora: I prethee who but the long-eard animall had rather heare the Cuckoe than the Nightingale? Whoſe eares are not more delighted with the melodious tunes of ſweete muſicke, then with the harſh ſounding drum? Did not <hi>Achilles</hi> delight himſelfe with his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13356:22"/>harpe as well as with the trumpet? Nay, is there not more men that rather affect the laudable vſe of the Citterne, and Bandore, and Lute for the recreation of their mindes, than the clamourous noyſe of drums? Whether is it more agreeable to humane nature to march amongſt murthered carkaſſes, which you ſay man reioyceth in, than to enioy the fruition of peace and plenty, euen to dance on ſilken Carpets, as you ſay, is our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? What man ſoeuer maketh warres, is it not to this ende, that hee might enioy peace? Who marcheth among murdered carkaſſes, but to this end, that his enemies being ſubdued and ſlaine, he may ſecurely enioy peace? Man loues to heare the threatning of his Princes enemies, but woman weepes when ſhee heares of warres, What man that is a true and loyall ſubiect loues to heare his Princes enemies threaten: is not this a ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation thinke you? is it not more humane to bewaile the wars and loſſe of our countrimen, then to reioyce in the threats of an aduerſary? but you goe forward in your paralelling a mans loue to lie on the cold graſſe, but a woman muſt bee wrapped in warme mantles. I neuer heard of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that had rather lie in the could graſſe then in a feather-bed, if he might haue his choyce; yet you make it a proper attribute to all your ſexe. Thus you ſee your cheefeſt elegancie to bee but miſerable patches and botches: this Antitheſis you haue found in ſome Author betwixt a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier and a louer, and you ſtretch it to ſhew the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt a man and a woman; <hi>ſed nos hac
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13356:22"/>a ſcabie teneamus vngues:</hi> I loue not to ſcratch a mangie raſcall, there is neither credit nor pleaſure in it. You threaten your ſecond volly of pouder and ſhot, wherein you will make vs ſnakes, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous adders, and ſcorpions, &amp; I know not what;<note place="margin">Second Epiſtle.</note> are theſe termes beſeeming the mouth of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian or a man, which is <hi>ouo prognatus eodem,</hi> did not your mother hatch the ſame Cockatrice egge to make you in the number of the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Vipers? and I take you to be of that brood which <hi>Homer</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, alwaies lolling out the tongue, and all the Hiſtoriographers terme <hi>Scopes</hi> that giue a moſt vnpleaſing and harſh note, <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, cauilling and taunting, and as <hi>Caelius</hi> wittily notes them to be ſo called, <hi>quaſi Sciopas,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hauing their face obſcur'd in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo this your booke being but the howling of a night-bird ſhall circumſcribe thy name in the dungeon of perpetuall infamy. Thou that art extold amongſt clownes and fooles, ſhalt be a hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and a by-word to the learned and iudicious: in ſo much as thine vnlucky ſhrieking ſhall affect thee with gaſtly terrors and amazements: neuer thinke to ſet forth more larums of your bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe, but as <hi>Labienus,</hi> who was ſirnamed <hi>Rabies</hi> madneſſe, becauſe hee vſed ſuch liberty of his detracting tongue, that he would without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard or diſcretion, rayle vpon all men in his exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate mood; When all his bookes and writings were made a bonfire of (which in thoſe dayes was a new-found way of puniſhing vntoward wits) <hi>Eam contumeliam</hi> (ſaith mine Author) <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bienus
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13356:23"/>non tulit neque ſuperſtes ingenio ſuo eſſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit. Labienus</hi> tooke ſnuffe at this contumelious deſtruction of his deſpiſed labours, he was vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be the ſuruiuing executor of his owne wit, whereupon in a melancholy and deſperate mood he cauſed himſelfe to be coffin'd vp, and carried into the vault where his anceſtors were entombed (thinking (it may be) that the fier which had bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his fame ſhould be denied him) hee died and buried himſelfe together. I doe not wiſh you the ſame death, though you haue the ſame conditions and ſurname as hee had, but liue ſtill to barke at Vertue, yet theſe our writings ſhall be worſe then fiers to torture both thy booke and thee: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tranſcribing ſome verſes that a Gentleman wrote to ſuch an one as your ſelfe. in this manner I conclude.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy death I wiſh not, but would haue thee liue,</l>
                  <l>To rayle at vertues acts, and ſo to giue</l>
                  <l>Good vertues luſtre. Seeing enuy ſtill</l>
                  <l>Waites on the beſt deſerts to her owne ill.</l>
                  <l>But for your ſelfe learne this, let not your hand</l>
                  <l>Strike at the flint againe which can withſtand</l>
                  <l>Your malice without harme, and to your face</l>
                  <l>Returne contempt, the brand of your diſgrace;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt women ſit vnmou'd, whoſe conſtant mindes</l>
                  <l>(Arm'd againſt obloquy) with thoſe weate windes</l>
                  <l>Cannot be ſhaken: for who doth not marke</l>
                  <l>That Dogs for cuſtome, not for fierceneſſe barke.</l>
                  <l>Theſe any foot-boy kicks, and therefore we</l>
                  <l>Paſsing them by, with ſcorne doe pitty thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13356:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>For being of their nature mute at noone,</l>
                  <l>Thou darſt at midnight barke againſt the moone;</l>
                  <l>Where mayeſt thou euer barke that none ſhall hear,</l>
                  <l>But to returne the like: and maiſt thou beare</l>
                  <l>With greefe more ſlanders then thou canſt inuent,</l>
                  <l>Or ere did practiſe yet, or canſt preuent,</l>
                  <l>Maiſt thou be matcht with enuy, and defend</l>
                  <l>Scorne toward that which all beſides commend.</l>
                  <l>And may that ſcorne ſo worke vpon thy ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>That neyther ſuffering nor impudence</l>
                  <l>May teach thee cure: or being ouerworne</l>
                  <l>With hope of cure may merit greater ſcorne.</l>
                  <l>If not too late, let all thy labours be</l>
                  <l>Contemn'd by vpright iudgements, and thy fee</l>
                  <l>So hardly earn'd, not pay'd: may thy rude quill</l>
                  <l>Be alwaies mercenary, and write ſtill,</l>
                  <l>That which no man will read, vnleſſe to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thine ignorance, and then to laugh at thee;</l>
                  <l>And mayſt thou liue to feele this, and then groane,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe tis ſo, yet cannot helpe, and none</l>
                  <l>May reſcue thee, till your check't conſcience cry,</l>
                  <l>This this I haue deſeru'd, then pine and die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et cum fateri furia iuſſerit verum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prodente clames conſcientia;</hi> ſcripſi.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
